Today's דף daf is ע"ז, Ayin Zayin, 77. And we are going
to catch up today if you can see by just looking at
ע"ז, Ayin Zayin, but we pick up at the top of ע"ו
עמוד ב, Ayin Vav Amud Bet, 76b. And we're dealing with three
possible answers to the question that the גמרא Gemara asks, which is
according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you steal a cow or a
sheep from the owner, and he's חייב דאחריות chayiv de achrayut and
he has to replace it. It's a חטאת chatas that he has
to bring or he took a נדר, neder, and therefore because he
has to replace it, even though it's קדשים, kodshim, it's considered like
it's his because he'll suffer the loss when it's gone. So therefore
you have to pay him כפל. kefel. All's well and good, gesundheit.
Then, though, you go ahead and you slaughter it or you sell
it, so you pay four and five. Well here's the problem. When
you slaughter it, it cannot be eaten. It's קדשים. kodshim. It's either
קדשים kodshim slaughtered... well we're assuming קדשים kodshim slaughtered out of the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so a sanctified dead animal is forbidden to
derive benefits from. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon himself is the one
that says that an act of שחיטה shechita that does not make
the meat permissible to be eaten is not considered an act of
שחיטה. shechita. So how do you get the case of four and
five? So we basically have three answers, two variations of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and then a ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Basically, רבי יוחנן's
Rabbi Yochanan's answers are you slaughtered it in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Either you slaughtered it for the sake of the owners, but
then the גמרא's Gemara's question is, but then you're not חייב chayiv
because then it was a way of giving it back to the
owners. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but that's with the purpose
you did it, but then the blood was spilled. So in the
end it never made its... the owners never got credit for it
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So it turns out that it
was a continued act of גניבה, ganeiva, but because of the act
of slaughtering, basically in the end the goal was for the blood
to be sprinkled, so or thrown, I should say. So then it
was a שחיטה ראויה, shechita re'uya, it was שחיטה shechita that would
have made, at least had the potential of making the meat permissible,
although that's exactly what we're about to explore. The other answer according
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, maybe even an easier one, is you
שחט shachted it in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash not for the
sake of the owners, so then the owner doesn't get credit because
לא עולה לבעלים לשום חובה, lo oleh labaalim lishum chova, שלא לשמו.
shelo lishmo.
It's not a returning to the owners, but the meat can be
eaten because it's going to be eaten by the כהנים, kohanim, it'll
be eaten by you who brought it if it's a שלמים, shelamim,
and therefore it is a שחיטה ראויה. shechita re'uya. The third explanation,
so those are two variations of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, two ways
of bringing it in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and the third
explanation is according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that you שחט shachted
it out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but it had a
blemish. And because it had a blemish, well first of all you're
not חייב chayiv for שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz because it's not ראוי
לפתח אהל מועד, ra'uy lepetach ohel moed, you couldn't have brought it
as a קרבן. korban. But we don't really care whether you violated
or not, I mean God cares, but that's not our interest. Our
interest is whether the meat could be eaten. And as we're about
to see, the fact that it has a blemish means that it
could be redeemed. You could redeem it because it was not since
it was not fit for going to the מזבח, mizbeach, the altar,
because of the blemish, it could be redeemed and thereby to that
presumably is what makes what makes the meat fit, its potential to
be redeemed. So that's now what the גמרא's Gemara's going to explore,
that in at least two out of those three cases, either the
blood was spilled or the blood or it could have been redeemed,
it still at the time you slaughtered it wasn't fit to be
eaten. It needed the blood to be thrown, it needed to be
redeemed and so on. So why does that still count as a
good שחיטה? shechita? Yes, Micah.
Are you just saying here's the גמרא's Gemara's not considering this technically
a גזול, gazul, in which case it would be a problem to
begin with, it would not be לא עולה לבעלים לשום חובה? lo
oleh labaalim lishum chova? Well I mean, but you're bringing it for...
גזול gazul is the פסול pasul of גזול gazul for a קרבן
korban is you steal it and you sanctify it, it cannot be
your קרבן. korban. This is the owner's קרבן korban that somebody else
is bringing for the owner. The fact that an act of... I
understand, you're right, it does not that that is the assumption that
that does not make it a גזול. gazul. I mean it is
a גזול gazul but it's not a גזול gazul from the perspective...
correct, you're correct about that. Okay, so let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so we'll start from the top of ע"ו
עמוד ב Ayin Vav Amud Bet just to read the third answer
I just said of the ריש לקיש Reish Lakish answer. וריש לקיש
אמר בשוחט בעלי מומין בחוץ. veReish Lakish amar beshocheit ba'alei mumin bechutz.
He slaughtered it out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's a
בעל מום, ba'al mum, you're not חייב, chayiv, but more importantly, because
it's a בעל מום, ba'al mum, it could be redeemed and therefore
it's considered a שחיטה ראויה. shechita re'uya. תוהא רבי אלעזר. Toyba Rabbi
Elazar. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar now, whenever I read the word תוהא,
toyba, I always think it means to be תוהה, tohey, was astounded.
The רש"י Rashi insists that the word here means he smelled it,
because from the word there's a גמרא תוהה בת תיהא, Gemara tohey
bat tiha, which basically means he was like, what's going on here?
It doesn't pass the sniff test. Yeah, exactly. So anyway, he was
trying to figure out how does this make sense? One minute, how
does this make sense? רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, according to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan that you brought it as a קרבן korban in the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
שחיטה מתרת, shechita matieres, is it the שחיטה shechita what makes the
meat edible? וזריקה מתרת, vezrika matieres, you need the throwing of the
blood, so it wasn't fit to be eaten at the moment of
שחיטה. shechita.
So how still why is it a שחיטה ראויה? shechita re'uya? וריש
לקיש, veReish Lakish, according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
שחיטה מתרת, shechita matieres, if it's slaughtered as a בעל מום ba'al
mum out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, is it the שחיטה
shechita what makes it permissible? ופדיון מתרת, ufidyon matieres, you need it
to be redeemed, otherwise it's קדשים kodshim and it's אסור בהנאה. assur
behana'ah. Okay, now by the way, תוספות Tosafos says that the question
of a זריקה מתרת, zrika materes, because just asking generally, according to
ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan when you שחט shacht a קרבן korban in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, is it considered a שחיטה ראויה, shechita
re’uya, because it doesn't have the blood thrown? So a lot of
these תוספותים Tosafosims deal with the case of let's say there's an
איסור issur אותו ואת בנו לא תשחטו ביום אחד, oso ve'es beno
lo sishchatu beyom echad, right? You can't שחט shacht a mother and
a child, you know, calf or, you know, or whatever sheep on
the same day. Let's say I do, and I שחט shacht the
child sheep, I שחט’ד shachted the mother earlier today, and the child
I bring as a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and I שחט shacht it in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So
would you say, oh, שחיטה שאינה ראויה, shechita she’eina re’uya, because at
the moment you שחט’ד shachted it, you couldn't eat the meat because
you didn't throw the blood yet, right? So so תוספות Tosafos says
no, no, if eventually you throw the blood, then of course it
was a שחיטה ראויה. shechita re’uya. The question in the גמרא Gemara
here is not this answer of ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that was
brought שלא לשמו בעלים. she-lo lishmo ba’alim. If the blood is thrown,
then we look retroactively look back and we say the שחיטה shechita
was part of the process of making it מותר, muttar, and eventually
it did become מותר. muttar. The question is the scenario that the
blood was spilled, or the scenario that it was שחט’ד shachted out
of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. In that case, the meat never,
never became permissible. And since it never became permissible, okay, and it's
too late now to throw the blood, it's spilled, and תוספות Tosafos
assumes it might also be too late to redeem it, that's an
interesting question, can you redeem an animal that was once living that's
now dead? It's a whole question which I don't want to get
into. But anyway, that's what תוספות Tosafos says the real question is.
It's too late to do anything about it, and therefore it was
not, the שחיטה shechita didn't מתיר mattir it, okay? But if indeed
you did throw the blood eventually, you know, then תוספות Tosafos would
say well then that's more obvious that that would be okay. All
right, yes?
I don't understand why we need to see what happens in the
end. At the moment you're doing it...
I understand, but תוספות Tosafos is trying to deal with other גמרות
Gemaros and you would say a שחיטת קדשים shechitas kodshim is never
considered a שחיטה ראויה. shechita re’uya. תוספות Tosafos doesn't want to say
that.
No, I'm saying it's like, as long as like there's no other,
you know, מעכב me’akeiv beforehand...
But no, you need the blood to be thrown. Every קדשים kodshim
you need the blood to be thrown. So you're basically agreeing with
תוספות, Tosafos, right, it's only a problem when the blood wasn't thrown.
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא’s Gemara unclear about that. רש"י Rashi assumes
it's a question either way, all right? But certainly, so number one,
it needs a second act, so maybe that alone's enough to say
it should not be a שחיטה ראויה, shechita re’uya, or minimal... or
certainly it's a problem when it's too late to do that second
act. Okay, when that second act wasn't done and maybe can't be
done, so how can you say it was a שחיטה ראויה? shechita
re’uya? אשתמיטתיה, ishtamdesei, the גמרא Gemara says, so אשתמיטתיה ishtamdesei he forgot
הדרבי שמעון. had Rebbi Shimon. What’s the
case of ר' שמעון? Rebbi Shimon?
Again,
it's also another ר' שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, so it's all these ר'
שמעון Rebbi Shimons coming together. That ר' שמעון Rebbi Shimon says כל
העומד לזרוק כזרוק דמי, kol ha-omeid lizrok kezarak dami, anything that was
fit for having the blood thrown is like it was thrown.
And this is going to be, now there's always a question, whenever
you say כל העומד kol ha-omeid is it like x happened? You
know, what do we mean it's like that x happened? So do
you mean like, oh, okay, so I brought my קרבן korban even
without getting the blood thrown on the
מזבח? mizbei’ach? Like no, of course not. Like you need to throw
the blood to get כפרה, kappara, but what it means here in
all the cases we're going to be looking at are basically exactly
the same question: can I view it as if the meat is
fit to be eaten? Okay? So it's not a question of was
I יוצא yotzei my obligation... Let's say for example, or let's read
the next line. If it was fit for the blood to be
thrown, it was like it was thrown. וכל העומד לפדות, ve-kol ha-omeid
lifdos, if it was fit for the animal to be redeemed, כפדוי
דמי, kepadu’i dami, it's like it was redeemed. Now it doesn't mean
that literally. If I didn't redeem it and I got benefits from
it, I would be חייב chayav for מעילה. me’ila. I got improper
benefit from הקדש. hekdesh. If I didn't throw the blood, just because
I could've thrown the blood, I didn't get atonement, my קרבן korban
wasn't brought. But what it means is specifically in the scenario of,
do I consider this meat as being considered ראוי לאכילה? ra’ui la-achila?
Right? Even the word ראוי ra’ui is a hypothetical, right? Is it
fit to be eaten? Fit, well theoretically it was fit because you
could have done something to have made it fit. So if it's
considered to be a good שחיטה shechita to have made the meat
fit, if there was a scenario where it should have had the
blood thrown, it should have been redeemed, and that would have made
it fit, that's considered to be a good שחיטה, shechita, okay? So
let's take a look.
Okay, דתניא, de-tanya, now where you see this in ר' שמעון, Rebbi
Shimon, by another הלכה halacha that's to define the food as considered
to be food. One way we wanted the meat to be food
is to be a good שחיטה. shechita. The other way we want
meat to be considered food is the question of is it מקבל
טומאה? mekabbel tum’ah? If something טמא tamei touches it, it only becomes
food, it only gets טומאה tum’ah if the if it's considered to
be food. So let's take a look. דתניא de-tanya we taught in
a ברייתא, Baraisa, ר' שמעון אומר: Rebbi Shimon omer: יש נותר שהוא
מטמא טומאת אוכלין, yeish notar she-hu metamei tum’as ochlin,
there's a type of a נותר notar leftover meat of a sacrifice
that can have the טומאה tum’ah of foodstuff, ויש נותר שאינו מטמא
טומאת אוכלין, ve-yeish notar she-eino metamei tum’as ochlin, and there's a type
that cannot. And basically the answer the difference is, is it fit
to be eaten? Now once something actually becomes נותר, notar, the מצווה,
mitzvah, what's the מצווה mitzvah to do with meat that's נותר? notar?
You've got to burn it. Burn it, burn... Okay, I'm just kidding.
Anyway, that's everybody get everybody get that reference? No. Okay, fine. I'll
tell you afterwards. Anyway, so...
So that's not fit to be eaten. But נותר notar doesn't start
its life as נותר, notar, first it's meat first it's like קרבן
korban meat and then you left it over too long. So he
says in a scenario where the meat could have been eaten before
it became נותר, notar, even though now it's נותר, notar, it's still
considered food. If it started its life as being edible. But if
it did not start its life as being edible, then it's not
food. It's similar idea to what he says about שחיטה, shechitah, right?
שחיטה shechitah isn't שחיטה shechitah unless it makes the meat edible. Meat
is not considered food unless the meat was edible but as long
as it was edible at the beginning of its life, it's considered
food and it can become טומאת אוכלין.
tumas ochalin.
Well, let's take a look at the case, okay? So he says
כיצד, keitzad, what's a case? לן לפני זריקה, lan lifnei zerika, if
it the meat slept over, meaning it waited too long, the night
passed and you didn't throw the blood, אינו מטמא טומאת אוכלין. eino
metamei tumas ochalin. Then the blood was never thrown, it was never
fit to be eaten. So it's not food and doesn't get the
טומאה tumah of foodstuff. And exactly.
לאחר זריקה, le'achar zerika, if it's after
זריקה, zerika,
then it was fit to be eaten. So even though now it
no longer is because it's נותר, notar, מטמא טומאת אוכלין. metamei tumas
ochalin. It does have the טומאה tumah of foodstuff. Okay, but now
but that itself doesn't tell the idea of כל הראוי, kol harauy,
but then the גמרא Gemara says but this is a statement that
we've analyzed elsewhere, and where we've analyzed it elsewhere here's the conclusion
we've reached. דקיימא לן, dekayma lan, where have we concluded regarding this
statement? מאי לפני זריקה, mai lifnei zerika, what does it mean that
it became נותר notar before the blood was thrown? Or it means
קודם שנראה לזריקה, o kodem shenir'eh lezerika,
before it ever became fit for having the blood being thrown. לאחר
זריקה, le'achar zerika, if it became נותר notar after the blood was
thrown, does not mean the blood literally was thrown. It means לאחר
שנראה לזריקה. le'achar shenir'eh lezerika. As long as there was a moment
where the blood could have been thrown, then it's considered already to
be food and can become טמא. tamei. What would be the difference
what would be the scenarios it was never fit it was it
was fit? קודם שנראה לזריקה לן מאי היא, kodem shenir'eh lezerika lan
mai hi, what's a case where it became it stayed overnight before
it was ever fit to have the blood thrown? דלא הוה שהות
ביום למזרקיה. delo hava shahus bayom lemizrekei.
There wasn't time to do this זריקה zerika in the day. דשחטיה
סמוך לשקיעת החמה. deshachtei samuch lishkias hachama. You שחט-ed shacht it a
minute before nightfall, before sunset, and you could only throw the blood
and do the עבודה avodah in the מקדש Mikdash while it's still
daylight. So by the time you caught the blood, there was not
a moment the clock struck twelve or six or whatever it struck
the moment the blood was caught. So there was not a moment
to throw the blood on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And in that case
and then the night passed. So the meat slept over the night
without it ever having even had an opportunity to have the blood
being put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. That's a case where it's not
food. It never even could have had the blood thrown. One minute.
לאחר שנראה לזריקה לן, le'achar shenir'eh lezerika lan, if it was after
it was fit, דהוה שהות ביום למזרקיה, dahava shahus bayom lemizrekei, you
שחט-ed shacht it not a minute before nightfall, not a minute before
sunset. So you had the opportunity to throw the blood. Because you
had the opportunity to throw the blood, even if you never did,
it's as if you threw the blood for the purpose of saying
this meat in theory was fit to be eaten. And since in
theory it was fit to be eaten because you could have thrown
the blood, now it's fit to become the to have the get
the טומאה tumah of foodstuff. In that case מטמא טומאת אוכלין, metamei
tumas ochalin, it can get the טומאה. tumah. אלמא, alma, you see
from this, כל העומד לזרוק כזרוק דמי. kol ha'omed lizrok kezaruak dami.
It's like the blood was thrown. Again, not like the blood was
thrown like you get atonement for your sacrifice, but because it had
the opportunity, it's considered as if theoretically that it could have been
edible and that makes it considered food and it can get the
טומאה tumah of foodstuff. And that's why and that's why this is
and it's a very similar it's again it's not the exact same
that's not defining שחיטה, shechitah, that's defining food, but it's very similar
because the goal of שחיטה ראויה shechitah re'uya is to say you
made turned this thing into edible meat. So therefore since the blood
could have been thrown even if a minute later it was spilled,
if at the time of שחיטה shechitah it was theoretical to be
thrown, that's as if the meat is edible for the purpose of
foodstuff and as if the meat is edible for defining it as
a שחיטה ראויה. shechitah re'uya. So you could have a scenario of
spilling the blood and not and nevertheless be חייב chayav for ארבעה
וחמישה arba'ah vachamisha because it could have been thrown and that's enough
to define it as a שחיטה ראויה. shechitah re'uya. Yes, Charlie.
Two questions. You שחט shacht the animal, you sprinkle the blood and
then so in theory it's fit to eat but then you discover
it's a טרפה. treifa.
Yeah, well that's
not a שחיטה ראויה. shechitah re'uya. That would be a perfect example
of a שחיטה שאינה ראויה shechitah she'eina re'uya because then it was
never fit.
Second
this second case where you שחט shacht it right before the end
of the day, in practice that would seem to be only possible
with a קרבן פסח korban Pesach because normally the last קרבן korban
would be the קרבן תמיד. korban Tamid.
Yeah, yeah although בדיעבד bedi'eved if you got out of order it's
still כשר, kosher, but that's a good point. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's the case that it
should the blood should have been thrown, now, that and and that
defines it as fit to be eaten the meat and now the
גמרא. Gemara. So we're going to say the same thing about the
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish's* answer where it was a בעל
מום ba'al mum, *baal mum* שחט *shochted* out of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* where even if you never redeemed it and
maybe according to תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* you're not even able to redeem
it after its dead because it was fit to be redeemed that
also makes it considered to be food, okay, and a good שחיטה
shechita. *shechita*, okay. אלמא כל העומד לפדות כפדוי דמי *Alma, kol ha'omed
lifdos k'padui dami*. Where do you get this? דתניא d'tanya *D'tanya*, we
learned in a ברייתא braisa: *Braisia*. רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon? אומר *Rabbi
Shimon omer*, Rabbi Shimon says, notice how it's all רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, it's beautiful all the רבי שמעוןs Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi
Shimon's* are coming together. Okay, פרה מטמאה טומאת אוכלין הואיל והיתה לה
שעת הכושר *Para metame'a tumas ochlin ho'il v'hayesa la sha'as hakosher*. So
now you can just remember those eight words and you can learn
an עמוד *amud* of גמרא Gemara *Gemara* every second. Okay, so anyway
a פרה *para*, פרה אדומה *para aduma*, okay which by the way
interestingly a פרה אדומה *para aduma* is considered קדשי בדק הבית *kodshei
bedek habayis* not קדשי מזבח *kodshei mizbe'ach* because it's not actually a
קרבן korban *korban*, although it's similar to a קרבן korban *korban*, it's
a fascinating sort of hybrid status of a פרה אדומה *para aduma*.
Okay, you and the question is if some same question of טומאת
אוכלין *tumas ochlin*, can it get the טומאה *tuma* of foodstuffs? If
something טמא *tamei* touches it will it become טמא *tamei*? Now if
you're wondering what this huge
תוספות *Tosafos* is about, I'll just tell you, one of the things
this huge תוספות *Tosafos* is about is about the fact that one
minute, I thought a פרה אדומה *para aduma* causes people to become
טמא *tamei*, it itself is a source of טומאה *tuma*. So if
a פרה אדומה *para aduma* is itself a source of טומאה *tuma*,
why does it have to talk about a scenario where it gets
טומאה *tuma* from outside? Okay, so תוספות *Tosafos* tries to work through
that, but the simple answer is that it's only a source of
טומאה *tuma* if you're involved in the process of of making it
into the ashes and so on, not just simple touching would not
be a source of טומאה *tuma*. But anyway, so can a פרה
אדומה *para aduma* that was שחט *shochted* be considered food? Okay now
again, the meat is never meant to be eaten, it's not like
bringing a קרבן korban, *korban* in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? *Beis
HaMikdash* where you or the כהנים *Kohanim* would eat the meat. It's
meant to be burned. It's קדשים kodshim *kodshim*. You're not allowed to
eat קדשים kodshim *kodshim*. So when is it ever considered food? How
could it be considered food to get טומאת אוכלין *tumas ochlin*? So
it says it can get טומאת אוכלין *tumas ochlin*, why? What's the
scenario that it could be eaten? הואיל והיתה לה שעת הכושר *Ho'il
v'hayesa la sha'as hakosher*. It had a moment where it could have
been eaten. What was that moment? So we're going to explain, turn
the עמוד *amud*, turn the page. ואמר ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *V'amar
Reish Lakish*, said ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish*, אמר Ama, היה
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon, *Omer haya Rabbi Shimon*, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
*Rabbi Shimon* again notice it's again a ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish
Lakish* and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, it's all the same
players, רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* used to say, פרה נפדית על גבי
מערכתה *Para nifdeis al gabei maarachta*, a
פרה *para* could be redeemed even if you have the dead carcass
sitting on top of the pyre, right, you know the pile of
wood, you're about to light it, you know you're about to start
burning it, okay, the moment before you start burning it you can
decide, you know what, it's sort of like you know we should
do this better, like I found a better פרה אדומה *para aduma*,
maybe I didn't have the right כוונות *kavanos*, I'm just teasing about
that, anyway, so let's go ahead, we'll redeem it, we'll start right,
we'll start the whole process again. Even up to the last minute.
Now תוספות *Tosafos* says בעלי תוספות *Baalei Tosafos* says presumably we're talking
before you did זריקת הדם *zrikas hadam*, like once you did זריקת
הדם *zrikas hadam*, you know that's it. But okay, but up to
almost up to the last minute you can redeem it and start
the process again. Okay, so there you go, it's fit to be
redeemed. So the fact that it's fit to be redeemed, even though
there's no מצווה *mitzva* to redeem it, and this way it's a
bigger חידוש chiddush *chiddush* than this זריקת הדם *zrikas hadam*, because there
is a מצווה *mitzva* to throw the blood of a blood of
a קרבן korban. *korban*, but here there's no מצווה *mitzva* to redeem
it, it's just in theory you could redeem it, it's enough to
make the thing considered to be food. Since it had a moment
where it could have been redeemed and it could have been edible
after it was שחט *shochted*, it's food and it can become טמא
*tamei*. And similarly, when I שחט *shocht* this בעל מום *baal mum*,
this animal with a blemish outside the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* for
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish*, that is considered a שחיטה shechita
ראויה *shechita re'uya* because the food in theory could be eaten if
I were to just redeem it. אלמא *Alma*, you see, כל העומד
לפדות כפדוי דמי *kol ha'omed lifdos k'padui dami*, anything that's fit to
be redeemed is like it was redeemed. See that was such an
easy גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. No I'm serious, like conceptually what we just
read is not hard, it's compared to stuff we've been dealing with.
But תוספות *Tosafos*, you know has these big other questions that are
not relevant to us, so it makes today's דף *daf* an easy
one. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. בשלמא *Bishlama* רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan
*Rabbi Yochanan* when there's a big רש"י Rashi *Rashi* there exactly.
Big תוספות *Tosafos* and you often do not have to worry. בשלמא
*Bishlama*, and not only that, relative to other תוספותים *Tosafosim*, those are
not hard תוספותים *Tosafosim*. I mean I know it sounds counter-intuitive, but
anyway, just long. בשלמא *Bishlama* רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan לא lo, אמר
כריש לקיש *Rabbi Yochanan lo amar k'Reish Lakish*. Now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara's* got got it, I got now the פשט pshat *pshat*, the
פשט *pshat* of why this שחיטת קדשים kodshim *shechitas kodshim* you're חייב
chayav *chayav* for in five is either it was a קרבן korban.
*korban* brought in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* or it was בעל
מום *baal mum* שחט *shochted* outside and in theory it could have
been eaten if you would have thrown the blood or redeemed it,
שחיטה shechita ראויה *shechita re'uya*. Now let's figure out why רבי יוחנן
Rebbe Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* didn't give ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish's*
answer and vice versa. בשלמא *Bishlama* רבי יוחנן לא אמר כריש לקיש
*Rabbi Yochanan lo amar k'Reish Lakish*, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* didn't say
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish* that it was a בעל מום
*baal mum* שחט *shochted* out of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* דקבעי
לאוקמי מתניתין אפילו בתמימים *d'kabai l'okme masnisin afilu b'smimim*. He didn't want
to limit our משנה *mishna* to a case of בעל מום *baal
mum*. He didn't disagree with ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish*, sure
if it was a בעל מום *baal mum* that would also be
a scenario, but I don't want to limit our משנה *mishna* to
that case. Our משנה could apply even if the animal was unblemished
and you brought it in the בית המקדש. אלא Ela ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish. מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב יוחנן? mai ta'ama lo amar
k'Rav Yochanan? Why did ריש לקיש Reish Lakish not give רב יוחנן's
Rav Yochanan's scenario, an unblemished animal brought in the בית המקדש? אמר
לך, Amar lacha, he'll say to you a new point about טביחה
ומכירה. tvicha u-mechira. וטבחו ומכרו, U-tvacho o-mechoro, you slaughter it or you
sell it. כל היכא דאיתא במכירה איתא בטביחה. Kol heicha de-isa bi-mechira
isa bi-tvicha.
You're only חייב chayav for shechting it if you could have been
חייב chayav for selling it, and vice versa. וכל היכא דליתא במכירה
ליתא בטביחה, Ve-chol heicha de-leisa bi-mechira leisa bi-tvicha, if you can't be
חייב chayav for selling it, you're not חייב chayav for shechting it.
So what does that mean? It means an unblemished animal you can't
sell, right? Because selling, if I would have tried to sell my
קרבן korban, to Charlie here and it was unblemished, it wouldn't be
a sale. He can't take possession of it. If it was blemished,
I could sell it because the act of selling, the money he
gives me could be an act of transferring the קדושה kedusha to
the money and because it has a blemish,
does it lose it automatically?
I'm not exactly sure. But anyway, but at least in theory it's
possible. Okay, certainly you could say that that's what you're doing. And
so therefore, since it could be sold, I'm
also—there's a scenario I could be חייב chayav for selling it, I'm
חייב chayav for slaughtering it. But if it was unblemished and there
was not a scenario where I could be חייב chayav for selling
it, because no sale could take place, I'm not even חייב chayav
for slaughtering it. So this is a new idea of טביחה ומכירה
tvicha u-mechira for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that you have to be
able to be חייב chayav for one to be חייב chayav for
the other. כל היכא דאיתא במכירה איתא בטביחה וכל היכא דליתא במכירה
ליתא בטביחה. Kol heicha de-isa bi-mechira isa bi-tvicha ve-chol heicha de-leisa bi-mechira
leisa bi-tvicha. והני קדשים בקדשים האי דמיזבן קדשים לא הוי מכירה, Ve-hani
kodshim bis-kodshim hadei de-mizban kodshim lo havei mechira, if you try to
sell a קרבן korban without a blemish, it's not a sale. ליתא
בטביחה, Leis nu bi-tvicha, you're not חייב chayav even if you slaughter
it. What?
It says וטבחו ומכרו. u-tvacho o-mechoro.
I know, which is even funnier.
Which is that I understand, וטבחו ומכרו, u-tvacho o-mechoro, which means if
anything it's independent.
I understand, which is why it's funny that the גמרא Gemara had
a ו' vav in our text of the גמרא, Gemara even though
the ספרי Sifrei changes it back to the 'o'. Yeah, I don't
know exactly, but you know, the fact that it's just talking about
it in the same breath. But you're right. Exactly why it's seen
as this tight connection, I don't know. Okay, that's what ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish says. And the גמרא Gemara says, ואזדו לטעמייהו, ve-azdu le-ta'amaihu,
and guess what? We actually know that this is a debate of
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan and ריש לקיש that exactly parallels why they
chose—רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan chose to say תמימים tmimim and ריש לקיש
says בעל מום, we're not even making this up. Okay, this actually
they are known to have debated this question of is the חיוב
chiyuv of שחיטה ומכירה, shechita u-mechira, do you have to be theoretically
able to be חייב chayav for one to be חייב chayav for
the other? אתמר, Itmar, it was taught: המוכר טרפה, ha-mocher tereifa, let's
have a flip case where you can't be חייב chayav for שחיטה.
shechita Could you be חייב chayav for מכירה? mechira? You sell an
animal that's a טרפה. tereifa. Now according to רב שמעון, Rav Shimon,
as Charlie just gave this case, you can't be חייב chayav for
שחיטה shechita. because the שחיטה shechita, will never make the meat edible.
Good. So according to רב שמעון, Rav Shimon, are you חייב chayav
if you sell it for four and five if you could never
be חייב chayav, for shechting it? המוכר טרפה לדברי רבי שמעון, Ha-mocher
tereifa le-divrei Rabbi Shimon, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan אמר חייב, amar chayav,
you're still חייב, chayav מכירה mechira you're חייב chayav for, שחיטה shechta.
you're not. ריש לקיש אמר פטור, amar patur, you're exempt. רב יוחנן
Rav Yochanan אמר חייב אף על גב דליתא בטביחה, amar chayav af
al gav de-leisa bi-tvicha,
although you can't be חייב chayav for shechting it, איתא במכירה, isa
bi-mechira, you're חייב chayav for selling. ריש לקיש אמר פטור, amar patur,
no you're exempt, כיון דליתא בטביחה ליתא במכירה. keivan de-leisa bi-tvicha leisa
bi-mechira. If you can't be חייב chayav for one, you can't be
חייב chayav for the other. In the קדשים kodshim case of a
without a blemish, you're not חייב chayav for מכירה, mechira, so therefore
you're not חייב chayav for שחיטה. In this case, you're not חייב
chayav for שחיטה, so therefore you're not חייב chayav for מכירה. mechira.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: איתיביה eseiv רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
לריש לקיש, le-Resh Lakish, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
challenged ריש לקיש. Here we have a ברייתא: braita גנב כלאים, ganav
kilayim, you stole a high-bred animal, an animal that was a cross
between—רש"י Rashi says what's
כלאים? kilayim? רש"י Rashi says... what does רש"י say? נקבה ותיש. Nikva
ve-tayash. What's a
תיש?
tayash? A תיש, taysh, right?
Like a goat? A goat. All right, okay fine. Right, okay. So
can you make a high-bred between a sheep and a goat?
We looked at that when we were doing חולין, Chullin, we discovered
they've actually done that.
Okay. So an animal here is a crossbreed of a sheep and
a goat. Okay. So now, גנב כלאים, ganav kilayim, now the funny
thing here is, the reason that this is a חידוש chiddush to
say you're חייב chayav, for שחיטה-מכירה shechita-mechira is the Torah says כי
יגנוב איש שור או שה. ki yignov ish shor o seh. So
is this a שה? seh? A שה seh includes—you know, both—you know,
like what would a שה seh include, something that's a high-bred of
a goat and a sheep?
Okay, we talked about this in חולין.
Chullin. Yeah, I know. So let's take a look. Okay, so it
says: גנב כלאים, ganav kilayim, you stole a crossbreed, וטבחו, u-tvacho, and
you slaughtered it, טרפה ומכרו, tereifa u-mechoro, or a טרפה tereifa and
you sold it, משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. meshalem tashlumei arba ve-chamisha. You
pay four and five. So yes, כלאים kilayim is considered a שה,
seh, and selling a טרפה tereifa you're חייב, chayav. even though presumably—this
is רב יוחנן's Rav Yochanan's question—why did it talk about selling a
טרפה? tereifa? Because presumably shechting a טרפה tereifa you'd be exempt, but
selling a טרפה tereifa you're going to be חייב. chayav So it
says מאי לאו, mai lav, are we not talking רב שמעון Rav
Shimon here? According to רב שמעון, Rav Shimon, that's why it's a
חידוש chiddush, to say טרפה. tereifa. אמר, you see, אף על גב
דליתא בטביחה, af al gav de-leisa bi-tvicha, even though you're not חייב
chayav for shechting a טרפה, tereifa, איתא במכירה, isa bi-mechira, you're חייב
chayav. for selling, because obviously this is רב שמעון, Rav Shimon, why
else would it say selling a טרפה? tereifa? Obviously that's the point.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan to ריש... So
ריש לקיש says back: לא, רבנן. Rabanan. No, it's the רבנן, Rabanan,
and it says טרפה treifa because to tell you that they're not
concerned with שחיטה שאינה ראויה. shechita she'eina re'uya. So ריש לקיש says
one minute. The גמרא Gemara says back: אי רבנן טרפה במכירה איתא
ובזביחה ליתא? ei Rabanan treifa b'mechira ita u'vizvicha leita? So he says,
I don't get it. If it's the רבנן, Rabanan, why talk about
just selling a טרפה? treifa? Talk about shechting a טרפה, treifa, it's
a bigger
חידוש, chiddush right? ואלא מאי? v'ela mai? רבי שמעון? You want to
say it's רבי שמעון and that's why we talk about selling a
טרפה treifa because shechting a טרפה treifa you're exempt? But if that's...
but if that's true, כי, ki, why when it gives the case
of the crossbreed כלאים, kilayim, why does it talk about shechting a
כלאים? kilayim? Why doesn't it talk about shechting or selling a כלאים?
kilayim? בזביחה איתא במכירה ליתא? bizvicha ita b'mechira leita? So look, this
ברייתא braita is weird because it only gives one scenario for each.
It talks about shechting a כלאים kilayim or selling a טרפה. treifa.
So whatever you say about the טרפה treifa case, כלאים kilayim obviously
it's the same whether you shecht it or sell it. So it's
just picking one scenario for each but it doesn't mean to exclude
the other scenario. Okay, so that's what ריש לקיש says. So he
says, אלא תנא זביחה והוא הדין למכירה. ela tana zvicha v'hu hadin
l'mechira. Okay, so therefore, you know what, even if it were רבי
שמעון when we're talking about the כלאים, kilayim, it wouldn't be limited
to shechting, it would mean shechting or selling. So אלא אימא לרבנן
נמי, ela eima l'Rabanan nami, so I'm going to say the whole
ברייתא braita is the רבנן, Rabanan, תנא מכירה והוא הדין לזביחה tana
mechira v'hu hadin l'zvicha and it's not meant to say only this
scenario. So the ברייתא braita says shechting כלאים kilayim or selling a
טרפה. treifa. So רבי יוחנן is certainly right. By talking about selling
a טרפה treifa it sounds like shechting a טרפה treifa you'd be
exempt, selling a טרפה treifa you're חייב. chayav. But ריש לקיש says
look, it's a weird ברייתא braita because it only gives one scenario
for each case, one scenario for כלאים kilayim and one scenario for
טרפה. treifa. So I'm going to say this whole ברייתא braita is
רבנן Rabanan and it says one scenario but it really means either
scenario. Okay, which is a pretty weak answer as רבי יוחנן is
about to say. So the גמרא Gemara says back to him: האי
מאי? hai mai? What type of an answer is that? אי אמרת
בשלמא רבי שמעון, ei amart bishlama Rebbe Shimon, if the ברייתא braita
is רבי שמעון, איידי דתני טרפה בחדא, aidi d'tani treifa b'chada, since
the case of a טרפה treifa could only be one scenario, could
only be the selling scenario because the shechting scenario you're פטור, patur,
תני כלאים בחדא. tani kilayim b'chada. So once we're going to talk
about a טרפה treifa by selling because we have to be talking
about a טרפה treifa by selling, a טרפה treifa by shechting you're
פטור, patur, so we're going to give the other case by the
כלאים. kilayim. We'll say okay, a טרפה treifa by selling or כלאים
kilayim by shechting. Now we've got everything covered. Okay, that makes sense.
Okay, why? Because we had to pick one case by the
טרפה. treifa. אלא אי אמרת רבנן, ela ei amart Rabanan, but if
it's the רבנן, Rabanan, נערבינהו וניתנינהו? ne'arvinhu v'nitninhu? It doesn't make any
sense why we give them as separate descriptions and why we pick
one for each one of them. Put it all in the same
category. גנב כלאים וטרפה, ganav kilayim v'treifa, if you stole the כלאים
kilayim or a
טרפה, treifa, טבחן ומכרן, tavchan u'mcharan, if you shechted them or you
sold them, משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. meshallem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah. That's what
it should have said. It is so bizarre that it separates them
out and gives different scenarios. So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya.
Fine, you're right. This ברייתא braita is that I don't have a
good explanation about why it said it this way. I'm not conceding
the point, I'm still going to say the ברייתא braita is talking
according to the רבנן, Rabanan, but you're right, it's bizarre that it
gives one scenario for the כלאים kilayim and one for the שחיטה.
Not only that, what the גמרא Gemara should have made is even
a stronger point, which is there's no חידוש chiddush, according to the
רבנן Rabanan about selling טרפה. treifa. If it really was the רבנן
Rabanan and it was going to pick one scenario by the טרפה,
treifa, it should have been shechting טרפה. treifa. That's the חידוש, chiddush
right? The רבנן Rabanan disagree with רבי שמעון and say even if
the meat can't be eaten you're חייב. chayav So you know why
give the scenario of selling טרפה treifa which isn't the חידוש at
all? Give the scenario of shechting a טרפה. treifa. So רבי יוחנן
is clearly right that the פשט of the ברייתא brayta is that
it's going according to רבי שמעון and it's telling you that by
a טרפה treifa even though you'd be exempt by shechting it, you're
חייב chayav for selling it. So that's their debate about do you
need to be able to be חייב chayav one in order to
be חייב chayav the other. But now we've also introduced the כלאים
kilayim issue, so now we're going to switch gears and talk about
the כלאים, kilayim, a crossbreed, about the crossbreed. So let's take a
look. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
כלאים, kilayim, why are you חייב chayav by כלאים kilayim for גניבה
gneiva and for what do you call it, for slaughtering or selling?
שכתוב, shekatuv, it says if a person steals a שה. seh. Okay.
ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, and רבא Rava said, זה בני אב, zeh
bnei av, this is
a paradigm,
excuse me,
כל מקום שנאמר שה, kol makom shene'emar seh, anytime the Torah just
says the word שה seh by
itself, hold on, let me just check רש״י Rashi a minute, hold
on second. Okay
fine. Anyway, anytime it says the word שה seh by itself, בני
אב כל מקום שנאמר שה אינו אלא להוציא את הכלאים. bnei av
kol makom shene'emar seh eino ela l'hotzi et hakilayim. The word שה
seh by itself is meant to say not a crossbreed. So how
can we say, okay, we've had a debate about whether in order
to be חייב chayav for one you have to be חייב chayav
for the other. Okay, we've had we've had a debate about whether
in order to be חייב chayav for one you have to be
חייב chayav for the other. And that's a question about selling a
טרפה treifa according to רב שמעון. Rav Shimon. But we can all
agree that the ברייתא braisa, says you're חייב chayav for כלאיים. kilayim.
Why is that? The תורה Torah says שה Seh and רבא Rava
teaches us that any time the תורה Torah says שה Seh we
should assume that a crossbreed is excluded. Okay, זה להוציא את הכלאיים.
zeh l'hotzi es hakilayim. מה שדאמר שאני הכא דאמר קרא או לרבות
את הכלאיים. mah she'da'amar shani hacha d'amar kra o l'rabos es hakilayim.
It says שור או שה shor o seh and that extra או,
o, it seems to be extra, comes to tell us it doesn't
have to be exactly a שה, seh, it could even be a
crossbreed. So the גמרא Gemara, says one minute. דכל או לרבויי? d'chol
o l'rabuyei? Anytime it says the word או o or a sheep
or this animal, it's coming to mean even not exactly that animal,
even some type of a crossbreed? But I'll tell you show you
the exact opposite, דתניא we taught in a ברייתא, שור או כשב
או עז כי יולד, shor o chesev o ez ki yivaled, right?
This is talking about a type of an animal that you bring,
you know, you wait for the eighth day to bring it as
a קרבן, but it's basically also talking about what type of an
animal could be brought as a קרבן. So it says שור או
כשב, shor o chesev, an ox or a lamb or sheep. פרט
לכלאיים, prat l'kilayim, so the או כשב o chesev is to exclude
some crossbreed. Okay, או עז, o ez, שור או כשב או עז
כי יולד, shor o chesev o ez ki yivaled, an ox or
a sheep or a goat if it's born. So what's the extra
או o teaching you about the ox? פרט לנדמה, prat l'nidmeh, to
exclude a animal that even looks different. If it's born from two
sheep and it looks like a goat, okay, even though it, you
know, genetically is a sheep, nevertheless, that's also פסול pasul for a
קרבן. That's even less than a כלאיים, kilayim, that just looks different,
it's not actually a hybrid. Anyway, the point so being, the words
או o here rather than broadening the category are seen as explicitly
excluding things that are not exactly these. Okay, so what's the story?
Does או o broaden and you're חייב four and five for the
case of stealing a hybrid? Or does או o exclude, like by
the קרבן, and you can't bring a קרבן from a hybrid? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא, amar Rava, what's the answer? Says
רבא, Rava, הכא מעניינא דקרא והכא מעניינא דקרא. hacha me'inyana dekra vehacha
me'inyana dekra. In each case we're interpreting the או o based on
the context in the פסוק. pasuk. How is that true? הכא גבי
גניבה, hacha gabei gneivah, when it comes by burglary, דכתיב d'chsiv שור
או שה, shor o seh, an ox or a sheep, שאתה יכול
להוציא כלאיים מביניהם. she'atah yachol l'hotzi kilayim mibeineihem. If it would have
said an ox and a sheep, okay, an ox and a sheep
cannot crossbreed. Okay, a sheep and a goat presumably yes, but an
ox and a sheep cannot. Okay, so by just saying ox and
sheep, putting those words next to each other, implicitly it means no
crossbreed. Because ox and sheep are not crossbreedable. So by talking about
just those two, the implication would be no crossbreeds because that's, you
know, implicit about those two by themselves. So it would be true
even about a crossbreed of a sheep and a goat. So that's
if I would have just had them by themselves without the או,
o, I would have said no crossbreeds. Okay, או לרבות. o l'rabos.
So then comes the או, o, so the או o is coming
to tell me the opposite of what I assumed. Yes, crossbreeds. That's
in the case of
גניבה. gneivah. או לרבות כלאיים. o l'rabos kilayim. גבי קדשים, gabei kodshim,
דכתיב כשב ועז. d'chsiv kesev v'ez. Had it just written a sheep
and a goat, right? Because by קדשים it says שור או כשב
או עז. shor o chesev o ez. By גניבה gneivah it says
שור או שה. shor o seh. And there you can't crossbreed a
שור shor and a שה. seh. But by קדשים it says שור
או כשב או עז, shor o chesev o ez, a sheep and
a goat, and a sheep and a goat could be crossbred. So
by having them
juxtaposed, it would have suggested crossbreed yes, because crossbreeds are possible. שאתה
יכול להוציא כלאיים מביניהם, she'atah yachol l'hotzi kilayim mibeineihem, a crossbreed is
possible with a sheep and a goat. I would have thought that
so because by themselves I would have thought yes crossbreeds, the או
o is coming to tell me the opposite. או למעוטי. o l'ma'utei.
So the או o is coming to tell me no crossbreeds. Okay,
the funny thing about all of this is that תוספות asks that
where do you ever use רבא's Rava principle that the word שה
seh by itself excludes crossbreeds? Because here basically says, you know, you
go one way or the other, you're not clear where you start.
In one case you start in one position, the other case you
start in the other. It doesn't seem like there's any rule which
is the default position. Okay, but anyway the basic answer is that
by גניבה gneivah we use the או o to include crossbreeds because
we would have started with an assumption they're excluded. And by קדשים
we use the או o to exclude them, and not only exclude
crossbreeds, even exclude things that don't look like their parents, and that's
because we would have started by assuming they were included. Alright, so
we're 20 minutes ahead of schedule, let's get a little bit further.
Yeah, is that יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Oh my god, that's true.
Let's worry, got a month to worry about that. So the גמרא
Gemara says: Okay, והא גבי קדשים נמי נאמר שור או כשב. v'ha
gabei kodshim nami ne'emar shor o chesev. One minute. שאין אתה יכול
להוציא כלאיים מביניהם. she'ein atah yachol l'hotzi kilayim mibeineihem. You can't.
Why do you start by the כשב ועז, kesev v'ez, which suggests
crossbreeds and then the או o tells you the opposite? Start by
the beginning of the פסוק. pasuk. The beginning of the פסוק pasuk
says שור או כשב. shor o chesev. And an ox and a
sheep suggests no crossbreeds. So why not start there and say the
או o is coming to include? Right? Got it? Why start at
the end of the פסוק pasuk and say the או o is
coming to exclude? Start at the beginning of the פסוק pasuk where
it sounds like crossbreeds are excluded and say the או o is
coming to include. So the גמרא Gemara says
ונירבי, venirbi, ונירבי, venirbi, and then we'll include crossbreeds. No, מדסיפא למיעוט
רישא נמי למיעוט. mide-seifa le-mi'ut reisha nami le-mi'ut. If you know, says
the גמרא, if you start at the end, then the או o
is clearly coming to exclude. So the או o in the beginning
is also coming to exclude. And remember what we excluded from the
other או o was a נדמה, nidmeh, something that did not look
like its parent. גמרא says one minute, that's not an answer. Why
start at the end and assume exclusion? Start at the beginning and
assume inclusion. So the גמרא says אדרבה מדרישא לרבות. adarabba mide-reisha le-rabos.
So let's start at the beginning, say או o is coming to
include כלאים, kilayim, and then וסיפא נמי לרבות. ve-seifa nami le-rabos. We'll
use the או o at the end to also be including, you
know, include more animals. He says, היי מאי, hai mai, what type
of an answer is that? אי אמרת בשלמא למיעוט, ei amart bishlama
le-mi'ut, if you're saying the או o is coming to exclude, דאיצטריך
תרי מיעוטי. de-itztarich terei mi'utei. That's why you need exclude twice. First
you exclude כלאים, kilayim, a genuine crossbreed, and then you exclude from
the other או o even an animal that really is a purebred
biological offspring but whatever just because it looks different. Okay, so just
because you excluded the more severe case, you needed another או o
to exclude the less severe case. Okay, אי אמרת בשלמא למיעוט דאיצטריך
תרי מיעוטי דאף על גב דמיעט כלאים. ei amart bishlama le-mi'ut de-itztarich
terei mi'utei de-af al gav de-mi'at kilayim. Even though you've already excluded
crossbreeds because שור וכשב shor ve-kesev implies yes crossbreeds, the או o
excludes them. איצטריך למעוטי נדמה. itztarich le-ma'utei nidmeh. You need the other
או o to exclude an animal that doesn't look like its parents.
אלא אי אמרת לרבות, ella ei amart le-rabos, but if you started
by saying שור וכשב shor ve-kesev implies no כלאים, kilayim, the או
o comes to include כלאים. kilayim. Once you've included כלאים, kilayim, what's
left to include? Of
course an animal that just looks different would be included if you're
including a genuine כלאים. kilayim. אלא אי אמרת לרבות, ella ei amart
le-rabos, if you start at the beginning of the פסוק pasuk and
the או o comes to include כלאים, kilayim, תרי ריבויי למה לי?
trei ribbuyei lama li? Why do you need to be more inclusive?
What else is left to include after you've included כלאים? kilayim? השתא
כלאים ירבי. hashta kilayim yarbi. If you're including כלאים, kilayim, איצטריכא ליה
נדמה למירבי? itztaricha lei nidmeh le-mirbi? Do you even need to include
נדמה? nidmeh? נדמה nidmeh is ממש mamash a purebred biological offspring, it
just looks a little different. So if the או o is already
including, you're not going to need the other או. o. So clearly
we're going to start at the end of the פסוק pasuk and
say the או o excludes כלאים, kilayim, and then we'll need the
other או o to exclude not just a כלאים kilayim case, but
even a נדמה nidmeh case.
Okay, so then the גמרא is going to ask the question that
I just said a minute ago, which is then when ever do
you go by Rav that the default of the word seh means
to exclude כלאים kilayim since here we didn't even start with a
default? We started in one place we assumed yes, one place no.
Whenever does this default idea apply? We'll pick up with that tomorrow.
So you get a little free time now.